## Alberto Stefanelli

#### RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interest spans from voting behaviour, methodology, public option, to political communication. I have a specific interest in populism, democratic representation, personalisation and presidentialisation of politics, campaign and party finance, and machine learning and big data.

Centre for Sociological Research
KU Leuven

Parkstraat 45

Leuven, Belgium

**☎** | Mobile: +39 340 6360909 (Italian)

alberto.stefanelli.main@gmail.com alberto.stefanelli@kuleuven.be

#### EDUCATION

#### **2012 - 2015 Bachelor Degree**

1st Grade Degree in Political Science, International Studies, Public Administration University of Padua, Italy Avg. Grade: 28.53/30. Final Mark: 110/110. Magna cum laude

#### 2016 - 2018 **Master Degree**

MASTER OF ARTS (MA), POLITICAL SCIENCE
Central European University<sup>1</sup>,
Budapest, Hungary
Thesis Supervisor: Gabor Toka
Cumulative GPA: 3.83/4
Rank/Class Size: 1/10

#### 2018 - 2020 **Master Degree**

MASTER OF STATISTICS Faculty of Science<sup>2</sup>, KU Leuven, Belgium

#### 2018 - 2022 **Doctoral Education**

PHD CANDIDATE AT CENTRE FOR SOCIOLOGICAL RESEARCH Faculty of Social Sciences<sup>3</sup>, KU Leuven, Belgium.

Sponsor: Prof. dr. Bart Meuleman

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### PUBLISHED PAPERS

- [1] A. Stefanelli and M. Almagisti, "Costi della politica e finanziamenti: Il livello locale", in *Il finanziamento alla politica in Italia*, ser. Biblioteca di testi e studi (1189), D. R. Piccio, Ed., Carocci, 2018, ISBN: 978-88-430-8676-4.
- [2] A. Stefanelli, "The Electoral Consolidation of the Five Star Movement", English, *Quaderni di Scienza Politica*, vol. Il Movimento Cinque Stelle: Prospettive di Ricerca a Confronto, no. 3, M. Almagisti and P. R. Graziano, Eds., 2017, ISSN: 1124-7959.
- [3] M. Almagisti and A. Stefanelli, "Dove soffia il vento del Nord", in *Cambiamento o assestamento? Le elezioni amministrative del 2016*, Istituto Carlo Cattaneo, 2016, pp. 9–22, ISBN: 978-88-941126-2-7.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>Central European University (CEU) is a graduate-level, English-language university accredited in the U.S. In 2015, CEU ranked among top 30 Universities in Europe for Political Science.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>2</sup>According to QS Ranking, the Leuven Statistics Research Centre (LStat) is among top 10 program in Europe for Mathematical and Statistical Sciences and top 50 in the world.

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>3</sup>According to QS Ranking, the Faculty of Social Sciences is among top 20 departments in Europe for Social, Political and Behavioural Sciences and top 50 in the world.

[4] ——, "Voto al candidato presidente e liste personali e regionali. Il Veneto in prospettiva comparata", IT, *DEMOCRAZIA E DIRITTO*, no. 3, pp. 44–62, 2015, ISSN: 1972-5590. DOI: 10.3280/DED2015-003003. [Online]. Available: http://www.francoangeli.it/Riviste/Scheda\_rivista.aspx?idArticolo=56057.

#### Papers under review

[5] A. Stefanelli, "Populist voters are irrational. Testing spatial models using populist attitudes", Accepted in the special issue The Political Psychology of Populism on the European Journal of Political Research (EJPR). Editiors: Ryan E. Carlin, Kirk A. Hawkins, and Levente Littvay.

#### SELECTED CONFERENCE TALKS

- [6] A. Stefanelli, "The Downsian irrationality of Populist Voters. Testing spatial models using populist attitudes", Politicologenetmaal Conference, Leiden, 2018.
- [7] —, "Populist voters are irrational. Testing spatial models using populist attitudes", Team Populism Conference (invited), Budapest, 2017.
- [8] —, "Competence or Proximity? Insights from a conjoint experiment", Urbino, 2017.
- [9] —, "Il M5s alle urne: Elezioni nazionali e amministrative a confronto", (invited), University of Padua, Nov. 2016.
- [10] A. Stefanelli and M. Almagisti, "Costi della politica e finanziamenti: Il livello locale", (invited), University of Turin, 2016.
- [11] —, "Il voto di preferenza nelle principali città al voto", 2016.
- [12] M. Almagisti, N. Scarnera, and A. Stefanelli, "Tendenze nel voto in Veneto: Voto di preferenza e voto al candidato presidente", 2015.
- [13] M. Almagisti, A. Innocenzio, and A. Stefanelli, "Una prima analisi della campagna per le elezioni regionali del Veneto 2015", 2015.

#### WORKING PAPER

A.Stefanelli, "Categorical classification and vote choice. A predicting model using machine learning"

F. Vegetti, S. Belli, A.Stefanelli, "The 2016 Italian Constitutional Referendum: Protest or Economic Voting?"

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### SUMMER 2018 TA for Automated Collection of Web and Social Data (ECPR)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY Teaching Assistant in the Automated Collection of Web and Social Data at the 2018 ECPR Method School in Budapest. Instructor: Pablo Barberá

#### SUMMER 2018 TA for R Basics (ECPR)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY Teaching Assistant in the R Basics course at the 2018 ECPR Method School in Budapest. Instructor: Akos Mate

#### SPRING 2018 TA for Text Mining Boot Camp

Central European University, Budapest, Hungary Teaching Assistant in the Text Mining Boot Camp. Introduction to Text Mining with R. Instructor: Jessie Labov and Littvay (Levi) Levente

#### MAY 2018 TA for Regression Refresher (ECPR)

UNIVERSITY OF BAMBERG, BAMBERG, GERMANY

Teaching Assistant at the Winter School in Methods and Techniques organised by the European Consortium for Political Research (ECPR)

#### WINTER 2018 TA for Experimental Political Science

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

Teaching Assistant and guest speaker (Human Intelligence Task platforms) in the Experimental Political Science course. Instructor: Littvay (Levi) Levente

#### FALL 2017 TA for Text Analysis Across Discipline

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

Teaching Assistant (data management and analysis) in the university wise course Text Analysis Across Discipline. Instructor: Jessie Labov

#### 2016 Introductory seminars at bachelor level

UNIVERSITY OF PADUA, ITALY

Guess speaker for two seminar on political communication and campaigning (with Mario Rodriguez) and regional electoral systems (with Marco Almagisti). Instructor: Marco Almagisti

#### ACADEMIC HONOURS AND AWARDS

#### 2016 - 2018 Advanced certificate in Research Methodology and Social Analysis

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

## JUNE 2018 Travel Grant for the Politicologenetmaal Conference in Leiden, Netherlands. (400 EUR)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

#### MARCH 2018 2018 Winter School Grant (250 EUR)

ECPR METHODS SCHOOL, BAMBER, GERMANY

#### JAN. 2018 Research Grant for the an experiment. (400 EUR)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

## SEP. 2017 Travel Grant for the Team Populism Conference. Organiser: Nebojsia Blanusia.

UNIVERSITY OF ZAGREB, CROATIA

# JUNE 2017 Travel Grant for the Italian Political Science Association Annual Conference. (450 EUR)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

# JUNE 2017 Travel Grant for the Hungarian Political Science Association Annual Conference. (180 EUR)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

# 2016 - 2018 Master's Scholarship recipient. Full tuition fee and health insurance. (26.000 EUR)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

#### 2015 Academic honour for thesis and grades excellence

University of Padua, Italy

Thesis title: Personalisation and Presidentialisation of Politics in the Italian Regional Elections.

#### OTHER RESEARCH AND ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

2018 - PRESENT Member of the Experiments and Survey teams of Team Populism<sup>4</sup>.

TEAM LEADER: RYAN CARLIN AND LITTVAY (LEVI) LEVENTE

2017 - PRESENT Vice president of the Central European University Populism Research Group (POPRES)

CENTRAL EUROPEAN UNIVERSITY, BUDAPEST, HUNGARY

#### OTHERS EDUCATIONAL EXPERIENCES AND TRAINING

- 2018 **Structural Equation Modelling (SEM) with R, ECPR Winter School, Bamberg** Structural Equation Modelling training (4 ECTS). Instructor: Ulrich Schroders
- 2017 Introduction to Time Series and Panel Data, Central European University, Hungary

Hands-on workshop on Time Series, Panel Data and fixed effect models (in R). Instructor: Nemanja Stankov

2017 **Web Scraping Workshop, Central European University, Hungary**Two-days workshop in Python on web scraping and data cleaning. Instructor:
Brian Fabo

2015-2016 Election Days, University of Turin, Italy

Workshops on political communication, campaigning and fundraising in a three days long seminar. The project is organised by Quorum/You Trend in collaboration with the University of Turin and La Stampa.

2014 Soliya Project, University of Padova, Italy

A virtual exchange program which entails weekly video conferencing sessions with other university students around the globe on issues concerning politics, intercultural integration, communication and new media technologies.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

AUGUST 2018 - PRESENT

ZK Analytics, Oxford Centre for Innovation, UK External consultant and analyst

Principal investigator for:

- 1. World Organization of the Scout Movement (WOSM) Measuring Scouting's Impact on the Personal Development of Young People. Propensity score matching and regression analysis
- 2. Ministry of Transportation of United Kingdom Capability, Health and Mobility of Older People. Complex survey design cross-tabulation and panel data analysis with fixed effect and conditional probit estimators

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>4</sup>Team Populism brings together renowned scholars from Europe and the Americas to study the causes and consequences of populism.

#### European Consortium for Political Research (ECPR)

### External consultant and analyst for the ECPR Methods Schools

Analysis and improvement of the questionnaires for the ECPR Methods Schools.

June 2018 - September 2018

Central European University

### Research Assistant for the Intellectual Theme Initiative

Data analysis, text mining and scraping, and data collection within the project *Text Analysis Across Disciplines* 

JANUARY 2015 - PRESENT

### Social Media Manager and Communication Specialist

Social media manager of various academic and non-academic projects (i.e. Il Voto Sotto Esame, Politica e Storia - SISP Standing Group, Team Populism)

OCTOBER 2014 - SEPTEMBER 2016

Research Centre "Centro Giorgio Lago", University of Padua, Italy

#### Project leader of a research project

In-depth analysis of the regional (2015) and mayoral (2016) elections of Veneto and Friuli (Italy). Project in partnership with Corriere del Veneto (RCS).

19 June 2016

# You Trend/Quorum for Sky TG, Turin, Italy Research assistant for SKY TG

Data collection for the 2016 Italian mayoral elections night, exit polls and real-time forecasts, post-electoral geographical maps using QGIS.

JANUARY 2014 - JUNE 2014

Research Centre "Centro Giorgio Lago", University of Padua, Italy *Team leader of a research project* 

Leader of the "Communication and Campaign" team. In-depth analysis of the communication and campaign organisation of the mayoral candidates of the city of Padua. Project in partnership with Corriere del Veneto (RCS).

FEBRUARY 2012 - JUNE 2012

## Campaign strategist and communication manager

Chief of the communication and strategy team for the electoral campaign of the mayoral candidate Annamaria Damiano (Desenzano del Garda, Italy.

#### OTHER EXPERIENCES

May 2013 - November 2014

Partito Democratico, Milano (Italy)

## Member of Statute Commission of the Italian Democratic Party

Review of national and Lombardy regional statute of the Italian Democratic Party (PD) according to the suggestions of regional and national elective assemblies.

#### LANGUAGE SKILLS

ITALIAN Native speaker

ENGLISH Oral: Proficient (C2) – Written: Proficient (C2)
FRENCH Oral: Basic (A2) – Written: Independent (B1)

### SOFTWARE AND PROGRAMMING SKILLS

PROFICIENCY LEVEL Linux, Mac OS, Windows

R, QGIS, Slack, SPSS, Phyton, LATEX

**GIMP** 

INTERMEDIATE Lexalytics

GGplot2, HTML, Markdown

BASIC LEVEL MySQL, STATA, PHP